<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.pism.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.pism.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2026-01-26T23:48:03+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PISM</title><subtitle>Website for PISM, the Parallel Ice Sheet Model</subtitle><author><name>The PISM Authors</name><email>uaf-pism@alaska.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Scientist for Modeling Ice Sheet–Climate Interaction at DMI</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2025/03/17/dmi-job/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientist for Modeling Ice Sheet–Climate Interaction at DMI" /><published>2025-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2025/03/17/dmi-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2025/03/17/dmi-job/">&lt;p&gt;The Danish Meteorological Institute (DMI), a leading research institution in climate and ice sheet modelling research, is offering a 3-year, full-time position as a Scientist for Modelling Ice Sheet–Climate Interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-of-the-job-advertisement&quot;&gt;Summary of the job advertisement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in working with climate and ice sheet models? And motivated by understanding climate change in the Arctic and Antarctic regions? Here is a great opportunity to join DMI’s skilled team of climate researchers at the National Center for Climate Research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Danish Meteorological Institute (DMI) opens a 3 year, full-time position for a scientist to work on climate modeling with a focus on the polar regions and how the climate affects the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our new colleague, you will work with our Earth system model that includes ice sheets as interacting components in both hemispheres. Your responsibilities will include designing and executing model experiments, improving the model code, and enhancing the coupling between climate and ice sheets. You will collaborate with colleagues at DMI and participate in international consortia. Additionally, you will analyze modelled climate outputs, lead and contribute to scientific papers, and participate in developing grant applications with our team and external collaborators.
Please use the following link for the complete job announcement and to apply for this position: https://candidate.hr-manager.net/ApplicationInit.aspx?cid=5001&amp;amp;ProjectId=187331&amp;amp;DepartmentId=6145&amp;amp;MediaId=5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current deadline is Sunday, the 30th of March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further details or questions about the position, please contact Christian Rodehacke at [telephone:] +45 3915 7453 or via mail at cr@dmi.dk. Alternatively, contact our acting Head of Unit, Mark R. Payne, at [telephone:] +45 2179 2620.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-the-job&quot;&gt;About the job&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our new colleague, you will work with our earth system model containing ice sheets in both hemispheres as interacting components: our comprehensive global earth system model EC-Earth, the Parallel Ice Sheet Model (PISM), and our surface mass balance model CISSEMBEL. You will be designing and executing model experiments and developing and improving the model code and climate-ice sheet coupling in collaboration with colleagues at DMI and as part of international consortia. You will also work with analyses of the modeled climate outputs, lead and contribute to scientific papers, and participate in developing new grant applications with the group and external collaborators. While working with the models and developing an improved coupling will be a core task, there will be some flexibility in deciding the weight between working with the model, running and analyzing experiments, and which particular topics and projects you work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polar research is a key research area in the National Center for Climate Research (NCKF), and our work is carried out in close collaboration with national and international partners (e.g., through EU Horizon projects such as PROTECT and PolarRES). As part of NCKF, you will work in a department with a strong profile in both global and regional climate modeling, as well as remote sensing. The position in the framework of the Horizon Europe project “LIQUIDICE” collaborates with sister projects “ICELINK” and “CRYOSCOPE.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-you&quot;&gt;About you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for a candidate with the following qualifications and experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A PhD degree in climate science, meteorology, oceanography, glaciology, or related fields (e.g., physics or engineering)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experience with modeling, preferably of the ocean, atmosphere, or ice sheets (e.g. global or regional atmospheric or ocean modeling, numerical weather prediction, Earth system modeling, surface mass balance or ice sheet modeling)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced programming skills (under Linux/Unix, scripting languages, e.g. Python or bash, high-level languages, e.g. Fortran or C++, etc.) and experience with HPC systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research experience working with polar (Arctic or Antarctic) climate is an advantage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good communication skills in oral and written English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-the-national-centre-for-climate-research&quot;&gt;About the National Centre for Climate Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position is in the Danish National Center for Climate Research (NCKF) at DMI, which employs more than 70 climate scientists, including PhD students, junior and senior scientists. The companion Weather Research department employs researchers working with meteorology, oceanography and hydrology. We have a strong international profile, which is also reflected in the many nationalities employed and in the use of both English and Danish as working languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NCKF has been established with the purpose to conduct critical climate research for the Kingdom of Denmark (Denmark, Greenland and the Faroe Islands) and bring together climate knowledge, to form the basis for green transition and climate adaptation. The activities include assessments of observed and future climate change of the physical climate system, with focus on the Polar regions and on extreme weather and sea level around Denmark. Across the department, climate research builds on both global and regional modeling as well as observations from remote sensing, in-situ measurements and field work. NCKF also develops the Danish Climate Atlas (Klimaatlas) which contains detailed data about expected future changes in the climate of Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-dmi&quot;&gt;About DMI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DMI is part of the Ministry of Climate, Energy and Utilities. DMI is the government’s climate science advisor, creating and communicating knowledge about weather, climate and the sea to the Danish Realm. DMI’s warnings, weather forecasts and services safeguard life and infrastructure and provide a basis for planning in a changing climate. As an authority on weather, climate and the sea, DMI provides meteorological services to the Danish defence, emergency preparedness as well as civil aviation and shipping in Denmark and Greenland. DMI is one of the oldest state institutions in Denmark and celebrated its 150th anniversary in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have approximately 400 employees, most of whom work at DMI’s new headquarters at Sankt Kjelds Gård in Østerbro. The new place have interior design that allows for an activity-based way of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;employment-and-salary&quot;&gt;Employment and Salary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will be according to the Danish Law and Agreements. It will be possible to apply for an addition to the basic salary. DMI offers a flexible working week of 37 hours including a paid lunch break, and six weeks of paid vacation annually. If you come from abroad, there is a possibility for a reduced tax scheme the first 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further details about the position, contact Christian Rodehacke (telephone: +45 3915 7453, mail cr@dmi.dk) or acting Head of Unit Mark R. Payne (telephone: +45 2179 2620).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At DMI, diversity is an important value for us, because we believe that an inclusive and versatile work environment strengthens task fulfilment. We work actively with diversity in our employee composition, which is reflected in our inclusive workplace with a balance between work life and family life. We encourage everyone to apply for the position regardless of age, gender, sexuality, religion or ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;application&quot;&gt;Application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Send your motivated cover letter and a curriculum vitae, so we have it no later than Sunday the 30th of March. We expect to conduct interviews during weeks 14-15. The invitation will be sent via email.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The Danish Meteorological Institute (DMI), a leading research institution in climate and ice sheet modelling research, is offering a 3-year, full-time position as a Scientist for Modelling Ice Sheet–Climate Interaction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PISM 2.2.1 is out</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2025/03/17/pism2.2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PISM 2.2.1 is out" /><published>2025-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2025/03/17/pism2.2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2025/03/17/pism2.2/">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of PISM v2.2.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changes-since-v220&quot;&gt;Changes since v2.2.0&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixed a minor bug: EISMINT II simplified geometry experiments should
use the &quot;cold&quot; (temperature-based) energy conservation model. In
PISM 2.2.0 the EISMINT II default of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;energy.model&lt;/code&gt; was
mistakenly set to &quot;none&quot;, i.e. isothermal mode without energy
conservation.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;To get correct behavior with PISM 2.2.0 run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pism -energy cold -eisII
\...&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pism -eisII \...&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notable-changes-compared-to-v21&quot;&gt;Notable changes compared to v2.1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All executables and scripts installed in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bin&lt;/code&gt;
sub-directory of PISM&apos;s installation location start with &quot;pism&quot; to
make it easier to recognize ones that belong to PISM, especially when
using a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.deb&lt;/code&gt; package to install it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rename the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pismr&lt;/code&gt; executable to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pism&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pismv&lt;/code&gt; executable. Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pism -test
X&lt;/code&gt; to run a verification test &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add some automatic testing on macOS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pkg-config&lt;/code&gt; to look for all the dependencies that
support it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the CMake flag &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Pism_PKG_CONFIG_STATIC&lt;/code&gt; to tell CMake
to use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\--static&lt;/code&gt; flag when using
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pkg-config&lt;/code&gt;. See &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;issue
529&lt;/code&gt;(https://github.com/pism/pism/issues/529).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;VERSION&lt;/code&gt; to ensure that tarballs with PISM&apos;s sources
(e.g. archived by Zenodo) contain appropriate version info.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update some examples in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;examples/marine&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fix an bug reported by Ken Mankoff: scripts in
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;examples/antarctica/&lt;/code&gt; required PISM built with PROJ.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a section about citing PISM to the manual; remove redundant and
possibly inconsistent recommendations elsewhere in PISM&apos;s docs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a section about publishing PISM results to the manual. This
section covers archiving the code, model inputs and outputs, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the configuration parameter &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;energy.model&lt;/code&gt; (choices:
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;none&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cold&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;enthalpy&lt;/code&gt;);
remove &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;energy.enabled&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;energy.temperature_based&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All bed deformation models use the load averaged over the duration of
the (usually long) bed deformation time step (see &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;issue
525&lt;/code&gt;(https://github.com/pism/pism/issues/525)). This requires saving
the time integral of the load since the last bed deformation update
(variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bed_def_load_accumulator&lt;/code&gt; and the time of the
last update &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;time_bed_deformation&lt;/code&gt;) as a part of the model
state and reading them when re-starting the model. Rename
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bed_deformation.lc.update_interval&lt;/code&gt; to
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bed_deformation.update_interval&lt;/code&gt; since now &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; bed
deformation models use this parameter. Add a new diagnostic variable:
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bed_def_load&lt;/code&gt;, the load used during the last bed
deformation update.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replace the serial connected component labeling algorithm with a
parallel version (see &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pull request
547&lt;/code&gt;(https://github.com/pism/pism/pull/547) for details). This should
improve strong scaling of the ocean model PICO and (less noticeably)
of some other PISM components.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Require CMake 3.16 or newer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support the current PETSc version (3.22).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update the oldest supported PETSc version from 3.7 to 3.11. (PISM&apos;s
code still works with PETSc 3.7 and newer, but testing with PETSc
older than 3.11 requires Python 2.7.x, which is no longer supported.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refactor the SSAFD solver, adding the ability to use PETSc&apos;s
infrastructure to manage Picard iterations (and even use Newton
iterations with a finite difference approximation of the Jacobian
computed using coloring). Unfortunately this approach appears to be
more fragile than the old one, so the default solver implementation
remains the same. On the plus side, we get the ability to compute and
save the SSAFD residual, which may help one analyze the quality of a
velocity approximation produced by the SSAFD solver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a Debian (Ubuntu) PISM package. This work required a number of
changes to follow best practices when installing software in a
standard location. For example: Python scripts in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;util/&lt;/code&gt;
are installed in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/usr/share/pism/bin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a configuration flag
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;stress_balance.ssa.fd.upstream_surface_slope_approximation&lt;/code&gt;.
If &quot;yes&quot; (the default), use the first order &quot;upstream&quot; (more
accurately: &quot;uphill&quot;) biased FD approximation. This reduces
oscillations of velocity approximations produced by SSAFD in areas
where the surface slope is large (e.g. near the grounding line).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a new diagnostic quantity:
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ice_mass_transport_across_grounding_line&lt;/code&gt; (in
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gt/year&lt;/code&gt;). This quantity is similar to the 2D
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grounding_line_flux&lt;/code&gt;, but designed to be easily
comparable to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tendency_of_ice_mass_due_to_discharge&lt;/code&gt; and
similar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use &quot;kelvin&quot; (lowercase &quot;k&quot;) in all temperature units and
implement other similar changes to make PISM output files compatible
with conventions used by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xarray&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add flexible re-projection and interpolation (including conservative
interpolation) using
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YAC&lt;/code&gt;(https://dkrz-sw.gitlab-pages.dkrz.de/yac/index.html). This work
makes it possible to set up a PISM simulation using a grid in one
projection and read inputs from NetCDF files that use &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;
grids and projections (with some limitations). This should reduce the
amount of pre-processing needed to use bed topography data sets (such
as BedMachine), regional climate model outputs, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve support for coordinate reference system specification
following Climate and Forecasting conventions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the configuration parameter &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.file&lt;/code&gt; and remove
options &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-x_range&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-y_range&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-refinement_factor&lt;/code&gt;. The parameter
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.file&lt;/code&gt; specifies the &lt;em&gt;grid definition file&lt;/em&gt; used to
set the coordinate reference system plus default domain and grid
sizes. See the manual for details.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add configuration parameters &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.dx&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.dy&lt;/code&gt; (command line options &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dx&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dy&lt;/code&gt;). These parameters allow users to set the domain
size and location (using the input file, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.file&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.Lx&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.Ly&lt;/code&gt;) and then select the
grid resolution to use on this domain. Note that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.dx&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grid.dy&lt;/code&gt; are in meters, but PISM will automatically
convert to meters from units specified using command line options,
e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dx 5km&lt;/code&gt;. Domain half widths &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lx&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ly&lt;/code&gt; are re-computed to ensure that PISM uses exactly the
requested grid resolution (this may slightly reduce the domain size
compared to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lx&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ly&lt;/code&gt; provided by the
user).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove support for NCAR&apos;s ParallelIO library since (as far as we
know) no one uses it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">We are pleased to announce the release of PISM v2.2.1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MPI-GEA: PhD position on the interaction of ice sheets, ocean and sea level</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/10/08/phd-mpigea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MPI-GEA: PhD position on the interaction of ice sheets, ocean and sea level" /><published>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2024/10/08/phd-mpigea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/10/08/phd-mpigea/">&lt;p&gt;In the department of Integrative Earth system science at the newly founded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gea.mpg.de&quot;&gt;Max Planck Institute of Geoanthropology (MPI-GEA)&lt;/a&gt; in Jena, Germany, we are providing a three-year PhD position as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spp-antarktisforschung.uni-rostock.de/en&quot;&gt;DFG priority program “Antarctic Research with Comparative Investigations in Arctic Ice Areas”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for a highly motivated candidate, interested in working in an interdisciplinary research team, with a focus on the interaction and possible feedbacks between the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets via the Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) and relative sea-level change in a warming climate. Numerical model simulations with PISM coupled to the global solid Earth and sea level model VILMA and the ocean model MOM will be used to investigate tipping characteristics and potential inter-hemispheric effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position will start on 01 January 2025 or as soon as possible afterwards.
Application deadline: 03 November 2024
Detailed information: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bit.ly/3TRs5eP&quot;&gt;https://bit.ly/3TRs5eP&lt;/a&gt;
If you have any questions about the vacancy or require further information, please contact: albrecht@gea.mpg.de&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">In the department of Integrative Earth system science at the newly founded Max Planck Institute of Geoanthropology (MPI-GEA) in Jena, Germany, we are providing a three-year PhD position as part of the DFG priority program “Antarctic Research with Comparative Investigations in Arctic Ice Areas”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PIK Potsdam: PostDoc positions in ice sheet and Earth system modelling</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/21/postdoc-pik/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PIK Potsdam: PostDoc positions in ice sheet and Earth system modelling" /><published>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/21/postdoc-pik</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/21/postdoc-pik/">&lt;p&gt;A two-year PostDoc positions in ice sheet and Earth system modelling is available in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pik-potsdam.de/ice&quot;&gt;Ice Dynamics group&lt;/a&gt;, as part of the new Earth Resilience Science Unit (ERSU), at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pik-potsdam.de/en&quot;&gt;Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research (PIK)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position is part of the German Climate Modeling Initiative PalMod III, with focus on the interaction and possible feedbacks of the Antarctic Ice Sheet with the solid Earth, the global sea level and the climate. Simulations will be performed with the Parallel Ice Sheet Model (PISM) coupled to the global solid Earth and sea level model VILMA, to investigate tipping characteristics and potential interhemispheric interactions, in cooperation with ESM modelers within PalMod (CLIMBER-X, MPI-ESM, AWI-ESM, CESM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position will start on 01/10/2024 or as soon as possible afterwards.
Application deadline: 31 August 2024 !
Detailed information: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t1p.de/cwp18&quot;&gt;https://t1p.de/cwp18&lt;/a&gt;
If you have any questions about the vacancy or require further information, please contact: albrecht@pik-potsdam.de&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">A two-year PostDoc positions in ice sheet and Earth system modelling is available in the Ice Dynamics group, as part of the new Earth Resilience Science Unit (ERSU), at the Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research (PIK).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">U Copenhagen: 2 PhD positions in ice sheet modelling at the Niels Bohr Institute</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/16/twophd-dk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="U Copenhagen: 2 PhD positions in ice sheet modelling at the Niels Bohr Institute" /><published>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/16/twophd-dk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/16/twophd-dk/">&lt;p&gt;Two PhD fellowship positions in ice sheet modelling are advertised at the Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is in stability and tipping points of ice sheets in the Earth system, with a specific PISM connection.  This PhD is a collaboration between the Niels Bohr Institute and the Danish Meteorological Institute.  Application deadline: 25 August 2024.  Read more and apply here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://jobportal.ku.dk/phd/?show=162276&quot;&gt;jobportal.ku.dk/phd/?show=162276&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is a PhD fellowship in computational and mathematical modelling of flow and fracture in ice sheets.  This PhD is part of the Novo Nordic Foundation project PRECISE – Predicting Changes in Ice Sheets on Earth.  Application deadline: 1 September 2024.  Read more and apply here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://jobportal.ku.dk/phd/?show=162378&quot;&gt;jobportal.ku.dk/phd/?show=162378&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Two PhD fellowship positions in ice sheet modelling are advertised at the Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AWI Bremerhaven: PhD position Projections of future sea-level rise from coupled ice sheet-ocean modelling</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/07/phd-awi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AWI Bremerhaven: PhD position Projections of future sea-level rise from coupled ice sheet-ocean modelling" /><published>2024-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/07/phd-awi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/08/07/phd-awi/">&lt;p&gt;The Alfred Wegener Institute, Bremerhaven, is offering a PhD position in the field of coupled ice sheet-ocean modelling. The core of the project is to run simulations with FESOM-PISM (a coupled ocean-ice shelf-ice sheet model with evolving cavity geometries) for different 21st-century climate projections to obtain well-constrained trajectories of future ice mass loss from the vast Antarctic Ice Sheet.  Model results will feed into a fingerprinting method that considers the ocean response as well as gravitational effects and contributions from other sources. The final product will be a time series of global maps of regional sea-level variations that consider all of the most relevant processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full announcement can be found here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jobs.awi.de/Vacancies/1768/Description/2&quot;&gt;jobs.awi.de/Vacancies/1768/Description/2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closing date for applications is the 30th of August, 2024.  (not the 31st!)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The Alfred Wegener Institute, Bremerhaven, is offering a PhD position in the field of coupled ice sheet-ocean modelling. The core of the project is to run simulations with FESOM-PISM (a coupled ocean-ice shelf-ice sheet model with evolving cavity geometries) for different 21st-century climate projections to obtain well-constrained trajectories of future ice mass loss from the vast Antarctic Ice Sheet. Model results will feed into a fingerprinting method that considers the ocean response as well as gravitational effects and contributions from other sources. The final product will be a time series of global maps of regional sea-level variations that consider all of the most relevant processes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MARUM Bremen: open postdoc in ice-sheet modeling</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/06/05/postdoc-marum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MARUM Bremen: open postdoc in ice-sheet modeling" /><published>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2024/06/05/postdoc-marum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2024/06/05/postdoc-marum/">&lt;p&gt;MARUM - Center for Marine Environmental Sciences at the University of
Bremen is offering a position for one postdoctoral researcher in ice-sheet
modeling, in the project “PalMod III-From the Last Interglacial to the Anthropocene”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geo.uni-bremen.de/geomod/staff/mprange/open_position_MARUM.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.geo.uni-bremen.de/geomod/staff/mprange/open_position_MARUM.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;!!!THE DEADLINE FOR APPLICATIONS HAS BEEN EXTENDED TO JUNE 30th, 2024!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please submit your application documents until June 30th, 2024 to
Matthias Prange (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mprange@marum.de&quot;&gt;mprange@marum.de&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">MARUM - Center for Marine Environmental Sciences at the University of Bremen is offering a position for one postdoctoral researcher in ice-sheet modeling, in the project “PalMod III-From the Last Interglacial to the Anthropocene”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PISM 2.1 is out</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2023/11/27/pism2.1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PISM 2.1 is out" /><published>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2023/11/27/pism2.1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2023/11/27/pism2.1/">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of PISM v2.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notable-changes-compared-to-v20&quot;&gt;Notable changes compared to v2.0&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these were included in 2.0.x bug fix releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mass-transport&quot;&gt;Mass transport&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Added a flux limiter that ensures strict preservation of non-negativity of ice thickness
and therefore mass conservation up to rounding error.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This is a Zalesak-style limiter described in&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;P. K. Smolarkiewicz, “Comment on “A Positive Definite Advection Scheme Obtained by
Nonlinear Renormalization of the Advective Fluxes”,” Monthly Weather Review, vol. 117,
no. 11, pp. 2626–2632, 1989, doi:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-0493(1989)117&amp;lt;2626:COPDAS&amp;gt;2.0.CO;2&quot;&gt;10.1175/1520-0493(1989)117&amp;lt;2626:COPDAS&amp;gt;2.0.CO;2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Note that this approach (unlike modifications of the discretization of SIA diffusivity
in the Jarosch et al. paper mentioned below) works with &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; stress balance models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pism/pism/blob/v2.1/examples/bedrock_step/README.md&quot;&gt;Implemented a
benchmark&lt;/a&gt;
verifying mass conservation in an “isothermal SIA + mass continuity” setup with “rough”
bed topography.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This benchmark is described in&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;A. H. Jarosch, C. G. Schoof, and F. S. Anslow, “Restoring mass conservation to shallow
ice flow models over complex terrain,” The Cryosphere, vol. 7, no. 1, pp. 229–240, Feb.
2013, doi: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-7-229-2013&quot;&gt;10.5194/tc-7-229-2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;isochrone-tracing&quot;&gt;Isochrone tracing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implemented an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pism.io/docs/manual/modeling-choices/dynamics/age.html#isochronal-layer-tracing&quot;&gt;isochronal layer tracing
scheme&lt;/a&gt;
(see A. Born and A. Robinson, “Modeling the Greenland englacial stratigraphy,” The
Cryosphere, vol. 15, no. 9, pp. 4539-4556, 2021, doi:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-15-4539-2021&quot;&gt;10.5194/tc-15-4539-2021&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;surface-processes&quot;&gt;Surface processes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implemented the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pism.io/docs/climate_forcing/surface.html#diurnal-energy-balance-model-debm-simple&quot;&gt;diurnal energy balance model
dEBM-simple&lt;/a&gt;
(see M. Zeitz, R. Reese, J. Beckmann, U. Krebs-Kanzow, and R. Winkelmann, “Impact of the
melt-albedo feedback on the future evolution of the Greenland Ice Sheet with
PISM-dEBM-simple,” The Cryosphere, vol. 15, no. 12, pp. 5739-5764, Dec. 2021, doi:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5194/tc-15-5739-2021&quot;&gt;10.5194/tc-15-5739-2021&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atmosphere-forcing&quot;&gt;Atmosphere forcing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added support for 2D precipitation offsets in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-atmosphere ...,delta_P&lt;/code&gt;. If the input
file set using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;atmosphere.delta_P.file&lt;/code&gt; contains a scalar time series &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;delta_P&lt;/code&gt;, use
that as a time-dependent constant-in-space forcing. If the input file contains a 2D
variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;delta_P&lt;/code&gt;, use that as a time-and-space-dependent forcing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added support for 2D air temperature offsets in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-atmosphere ...,delta_T&lt;/code&gt;. If the input
file set using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;atmosphere.delta_T.file&lt;/code&gt; contains a scalar time series &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;delta_T&lt;/code&gt;, use
that as a time-dependent constant-in-space forcing. If the input file contains a 2D
variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;delta_T&lt;/code&gt;, use that as a time-and-space-dependent forcing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added support for piecewise-constant temporal interpolation of near-surface air
temperatures in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-atmosphere given&lt;/code&gt;: set
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;atmosphere.given.air_temperature_interpolation&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;piecewise_constant&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ocean-forcing&quot;&gt;Ocean forcing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added the ability to use ocean model components implemented in Python (see
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pism/pism/blob/v2.1/examples/python/pism.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;examples/python/pism.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;calving&quot;&gt;Calving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed a bug reported by Christian Rodehacke: calving mechanisms should not remove ice at
ice fronts adjacent to isolated patches of ice-free water (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pism/pism/issues/521&quot;&gt;issue
#521&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stress-balance&quot;&gt;Stress balance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved the initial guess of sliding velocity used when the ice front advances by
extrapolating velocity computed by the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SSAFD&lt;/code&gt; solver during the previous time step (set
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;stress_balance.ssa.fd.extrapolate_at_margins&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;false&lt;/code&gt; to disable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-conservation&quot;&gt;Energy conservation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PISM no longer attempts to correct energy conservation by freezing basal water.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;At each time step PISM checks basal enthalpy and if necessary modifies it to ensure
continuity of temperature in each &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bedrock+ice&lt;/code&gt; column. Sometimes this modification
creates energy; prior to this change PISM attempted to remove an equivalent amount of
energy by modifying the basal melt rate to freeze water stored at the base.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Under some conditions this basal melt rate adjustment &lt;em&gt;created mass&lt;/em&gt; by freezing more
water than available and even led to crashes with error messages stating that ice
thickness exceeds &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lz&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;input-and-output-diagnostics&quot;&gt;Input and output, diagnostics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added diagnostics &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tendency_of_ice_{amount,mass}_due_to_frontal_melt&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tendency_of_ice_{amount,mass}_due_to_forced_retreat&lt;/code&gt;. Renamed diagnostic
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;max_sliding_vel&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;max_horizontal_vel&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bug-fixes&quot;&gt;Bug fixes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added time bounds to scalar forcing files in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pism/pism/tree/v2.1/examples/std-greenland&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;examples/std-greenland&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixed a bug in the code ensuring non-negativity of ice thickness. (The old code added
too much ice in an attempt to ensure non-negativity – so much so that sometimes this
caused crashes with error messages stating that ice thickness exceeds &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lz&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Note that this “projection step” (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ice_thickness = max(tentative_ice_thickness, 0)&lt;/code&gt;)
should have no effect now: the flux limiter mentioned above is designed to ensure
non-negativity. We keep this step, however, to maintain the ability to keep track of ice
thickness changes due to conservation errors (if they ever happen).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixed bugs in scalar diagnostics &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ice_volume_cold&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ice_volume_temperate&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use CF-compliant units “&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;common_years&lt;/code&gt;” in forcing files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other&quot;&gt;Other&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pism/pism/blob/v2.1/CITATION.cff&quot;&gt;CITATION.cff&lt;/a&gt; to properly
acknowledge all contributions and to make it easier to cite PISM.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implemented UNO2, UNO3 and a couple of related transport methods (not used, but
available for future use; see J.-G. Li, “Upstream Nonoscillatory Advection Schemes,”
Monthly Weather Review, vol. 136, no. 12, pp. 4709-4729, Dec. 2008, doi:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1175/2008mwr2451.1&quot;&gt;10.1175/2008mwr2451.1&lt;/a&gt;.).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;realpath()&lt;/code&gt; to resolve relative file names. Now configuration parameters ending in
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.file&lt;/code&gt;, when saved to output files and in PISM output to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt;, contain &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt;
file names. This will make it easier to reproduce runs based on an output file.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added support for checkpointing the HTCondor way (see commit
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pism/pism/commit/3740c41df6f35fdf0d7501f96f5cab362f25a24b&quot;&gt;3740c41df&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-list_diagnostics all&lt;/code&gt; to print the list of all diagnostics, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-list_diagnostics
spatial&lt;/code&gt; for 2D and 3D variables, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-list_diagnostics scalar&lt;/code&gt; for scalar time series.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added code to generate &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pism.pc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pismicebin.pc&lt;/code&gt; for use with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pkg-config&lt;/code&gt;. This
will make it easier to use PISM as a library (to couple to a GCM, for example).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PISM’s build system uses &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pkg-config&lt;/code&gt; to look for some of the required libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refactored utility classes used to store 2D and 3D arrays.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replaced &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;examples/searise-antarctica&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;examples/antarctica&lt;/code&gt; based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1594/PANGAEA.734145&quot;&gt;ALBMAP
v1&lt;/a&gt; data. This avoids a dependency on &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10140224&quot;&gt;SeaRISE
data&lt;/a&gt; formerly hosted by the University of
Montana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">We are pleased to announce the release of PISM v2.1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Constantine</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2023/05/01/patience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Constantine" /><published>2023-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2023/05/01/patience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2023/05/01/patience/">&lt;p&gt;Dear PISM users and developers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s my pleasure to congratulate our software engineer and PISM mastermind Constatine Khroulev to the birth of his son, Alexander (Sasha). Constantine is now on paternity leave and hence I’d like to ask for your patience as answering PISM questions will take longer in the next couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your understanding,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html">Dear PISM users and developers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Joint GEUS-PIK workshop October 24-25, 2022</title><link href="https://www.pism.io/news/2022/10/26/geus-pik-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Joint GEUS-PIK workshop October 24-25, 2022" /><published>2022-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.pism.io/news/2022/10/26/geus-pik-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pism.io/news/2022/10/26/geus-pik-workshop/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/news/geus-pik-workshop-group-photo-2022.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Group Photo in front of GEUS&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group photo in front of GEUS.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nanna Karlsson and Liam Colgan hosted the first joint GEUS-PIK PISM workshop at GEUS in Copenhagen, DK, October 24-25, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/news/geus-pik-workshop-photo-1-2022.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;R. Winkelmann (PIK)&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ricarda Winkelmann &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pik-potsdam.de&quot;&gt;(PIK)&lt;/a&gt; introducing the concept of tipping points&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 15 reseachers from &lt;a href=&quot;https://eng.geus.dk&quot;&gt;GEUS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pik-potsdam.de&quot;&gt;PIK&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.au.dk&quot;&gt;Aarhus University&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmi.dk&quot;&gt;DMI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uaf.edu&quot;&gt;UAF&lt;/a&gt; attendend the first joint GEUS-PIK PISM workshop at GEUS. The participants presented their latest PISM and PISM-adjacent research interspersed with lively discussions  which data sets could be used for model initialization, calibrations and validation, how can we detect tipping points, what are the best practices to initialize PISM, and which physical processes are currently missing. The discussions continued during a visit to the GEUS roof where Nanna showed us the GEUS weather station and during the workshop dinner. Many started dreaming about joining field work in Greenland some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/news/geus-pik-workshop-photo-2-2022.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all already looking forward to the next joint workshop currently planned for October 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Liam and Nanna for organizing and hosting the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/news/geus-pik-workshop-dinner-photo-2022.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Group Dinner&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Group dinner Monday evening&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The PISM Authors</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>